Thank you for putting up these pictures of my colleagues over here.
شكراً لكم لوضعكم هذه الصور لزملائي هنا.
(Laughter) We'll be talking about them.
(ضحك). سنتحدث عنهم.
Now, I'm going try an experiment. I don't do experiments, normally. I'm a theorist.
الآن، سأحاول أن أجري تجربة. في العادة أنا لا أقوم بالتجارب. أنا عالم نظري.
But I'm going see what happens if I press this button.
لكني سأختبر ماذا يحدث إن قمت بالضغط على هذا الزر.
Sure enough. OK. I used to work in this field of elementary particles.
جيد جداً. حسناً. لقد كنت أعمل في هذا المجال للجسيمات الأساسية.
What happens to matter if you chop it up very fine?
ماذا يحدث إن قمتم بختمها جيداً جداً؟
What is it made of?
مم تتكون؟
And the laws of these particles are valid throughout the universe,
والقوانين التي تكون عليها هذه الجسيمات صالحة عبر الكون،
and they're very much connected with the history of the universe.
وهي مرتبطة بشدة مع تاريخ الكون.
We know a lot about four forces. There must be a lot more,
نحن نعرف الكثير حول أربعة قوى. لابد أن هناك المزيد أكثر،
but those are at very, very small distances,
لكن تلك على مسافة صغيرة جداً جداً،
and we haven't really interacted with them very much yet.
ونحن لم نقم بالتفاعل معها كثيراً بعد.
The main thing I want to talk about is this:
الشئ الرئيسي الذي أرغب بالحديث عنه هو هذا:
that we have this remarkable experience in this field of fundamental physics
أن لدينا هذه التجربة المتفردة في مجال الفيزياء الأساسية
that beauty is a very successful criterion for choosing the right theory.
أن الجمال هو طريقة ناجحة جداً لإختيار النظرية الصحيحة.
And why on earth could that be so?
ولماذا بحق الأرض يكون الأمر كذلك؟
Well, here's an example from my own experience.
حسناً، ها هو مثال من تجربتي الخاصة.
It's fairly dramatic, actually, to have this happen.
إنه كارثة حقيقية أن يحصل هذا.
Three or four of us, in 1957,
ثلاثة أو أربعة منا، عام 1957
put forward a partially complete theory of one of these forces, this weak force.
وضعنا نظرية مكتملة جزئياً لأحد هذه القوى، هذه القوة الضعيفة.
And it was in disagreement with seven -- seven, count them, seven experiments.
وقد كانت مخالفة لسبعة -- سبعة، أحسبوهم، سبعة تجارب.
Experiments were all wrong.
كانت كل التجارب خاطئة.
And we published before knowing that,
وقد نشرناها قبل أن نعرف ذلك،
because we figured it was so beautiful, it's gotta be right!
لأننا توصلنا إلى أنها كانت جميلة جداً، فستكون صحيحة!
The experiments had to be wrong, and they were.
وكانت التجارب لتكون على خطأ، وقد كانت خطأ.
Now our friend over there, Albert Einstein,
الآن صديقنا هناك، ألبرت إينشتاين،
used to pay very little attention when people said,
كان يعطي القليل من الإهتمام حينما قال الناس،
"You know, there's a man with an experiment that seems to disagree with special relativity.
"تعلمون، هناك شخص لديه تجربة تبدو مخالفة للنسبية الخاصة.
DC Miller. What about that?" And he would say, "Aw, that'll go away." (Laughter)
دي سي ميلر. ماذا عن ذلك؟" وكان يقول، " أوه، سيذهبون إلى المزبلة." (ضحك).
Now, why does stuff like that work? That's the question.
الآن، لماذا تنجح أشياء مثل تلك؟ ذلك هو السؤال.
Now, yeah, what do we mean by beautiful? That's one thing.
الآن، نعم، ماذا تعني بجميلة؟ ذلك شئ واحد.
I'll try to make that clear -- partially clear.
سأحاول إيضاح ذلك -- أوضحه جزئياً.
Why should it work, and is this something to do with human beings?
لماذا تنجح، وهل هذا شئ متعلق بالبشر؟
I'll let you in on the answer to the last one that I offer,
سوف أترك لكم الرد على الأخير الذي أقدمه،
and that is, it has nothing to do with human beings.
وذلك هو، أنه لا علاقة له بالبشر.
Somewhere in some other planet, orbiting some very distant star,
في مكان ما في كوكب آخر، تدور بعض النجوم البعيدة جداً،
maybe in a another galaxy,
ربما في مجرة آخرى،
there could well be entities that are at least as intelligent as we are,
يمكن أن يكون هناك كائنات ذات ذكاء على الأقل مثلنا،
and are interested in science. It's not impossible; I think there probably are lots.
ومهتمة بالعلوم. الأمر ليس مستحيلاً. أعتقد بترجيح أن هناك الكثير.
Very likely, none is close enough to interact with us.
مرجح جداً، ليس من بينها من هو قريب بما يكفي للتفاعل معنا.
But they could be out there, very easily.
لكن قد يكونوا هناك، بكل سهولة.
And suppose they have, you know, very different sensory apparatus, and so on.
وأفترض أن لديهم جهاز حسي مختلف تماماً، وهلمجرا.
They have seven tentacles, and they have 14 little funny-looking compound eyes,
لديهم سبعة مخالب، ولديهم 14 عين مركبة تبدو مضحكة،
and a brain shaped like a pretzel.
ودماغ بشكل قطعة بسكويت.
Would they really have different laws?
هل سيكون لديهم قوانين مختلفة حقاً؟
There are lots of people who believe that, and I think it is utter baloney.
هناك الكثير من الناس الذين يؤمنون بذلك، وأعتقد انها هراء مطلق.
I think there are laws out there,
أعتقد أنه توجد قوانين هناك،
and we of course don't understand them at any given time very well
ونحن بالطبع لا نفهمها في أي وقت بصورة صحيحة
-- but we try. And we try to get closer and closer.
-- لكننا نحاول. ونحاول الإقتراب أكثر وأكثر.
And someday, we may actually figure out the fundamental unified theory
وفي يوم ما، ربما نستطيع بالفعل معرفة نظرية المجال الموحد
of the particles and forces, what I call the "fundamental law."
للجسيمات والقوى، التي أسميها بال" المبدأ الأساسي."
We may not even be terribly far from it.
ربما لا نكون بعيدين بشدة عنها.
But even if we don't run across it in our lifetimes,
لكن حتى إن لم نعرفها خلال فترة حياتنا،
we can still think there is one out there,
ما يزال يمكننا الإعتقاد بأن هناك واحدة منها،
and we're just trying to get closer and closer to it.
ونحن نحاول الإقتراب منها أكثر وأكثر.
I think that's the main point to be made.
أعتقد أن تلك هي النقطة الرئيسية التي يجب أن نفهمها.
We express these things mathematically.
نحن نعبّر عن هذه الأشياء رياضياً.
And when the mathematics is very simple --
وحينما تكون الرياضيات بسيطة للغاية--
when in terms of some mathematical notation,
حينما تكون متعلقة ببعض المفاهيم الرياضية،
you can write the theory in a very brief space, without a lot of complication --
يمكنك كتابة النظرية في مساحة مختصرة جداً، بدون الكثير من التعقيدات--
that's essentially what we mean by beauty or elegance.
ذلك في الأساس ما نعنيه بالجمال أو الأناقة.
Here's what I was saying about the laws. They're really there.
هذا ما كنت أقوله حول القوانين. إنها حقاً هناك.
Newton certainly believed that.
نيوتن بالتأكيد كان يؤمن بذلك.
And he said, here, "It is the business of natural philosophy to find out those laws."
وقد قال، هنا، " إنها مهمة الفلسفة الطبيعية أن تجد تلك القوانين."
The basic law, let's say -- here's an assumption.
القانون الأساسي، لنقل -- ها هو إفتراض.
The assumption is that the basic law really takes the form
الإفتراض هو أن القانون الأساسي يأخذ شكل
of a unified theory of all the particles.
النظرية الموحدة لكل الجسيمات.
Now, some people call that a theory of everything.
الآن، بعض الناس يسمونها بنظرية كل شئ.
That's wrong because the theory is quantum mechanical.
وذلك خطأ، لأن النظرية هي ميكانيكا الكم.
And I won't go into a lot of stuff about quantum mechanics and what it's like, and so on.
ولن أدخل في الكثير من التفاصيل حول ميكانيكا الكم وكيف تبدو، وهلمجرا.
You've heard a lot of wrong things about it anyway. (Laughter)
لقد سمعتم الكثير من الأشياء الخاطئة حولها على أي حال. (ضحك).
There are even movies about it with a lot of wrong stuff.
حتى أن هناك أفلام حولها تحوي الكثير من الأشياء الخاطئة.
But the main thing here is that it predicts probabilities.
لكن الشئ المهم هنا هي أنها تتوقع إحتمالات.
Now, sometimes those probabilities are near certainties.
الآن، بعض الأحيان هذه الإحتمالات تقترب من اليقين.
And in a lot of familiar cases, they of course are.
وفي الكثير من الحالات الشهيرة، كانت بالطبع صحيحة.
But other times they're not, and you have only probabilities for different outcomes.
لكن في أوقات أخرى لم تكن كذلك، وتحصل على إحتمالات لنتائج مختلفة فقط.
So what that means is that the history of the universe is not determined just by the fundamental law.
إذاً الذي يعنيه ذلك هو أن تاريخ الكون ليس محدداً بالقانون الأساسي فقط.
It's the fundamental law and this incredibly long series of accidents,
إنه القانون الأساس وهذه السلسلة الطويلة من الحوادث غير المعقولة،
or chance outcomes, that are there in addition.
أو فرصة النتائج ، التي هناك بالإضافة لذلك.
And the fundamental theory doesn't include those chance outcomes; they are in addition.
والنظرية الأساسية لا تشمل فرص النتائج تلك. إنها إضافة.
So it's not a theory of everything. And in fact, a huge amount of the information
لذا فهي ليست نظرية لكل شئ. وفي الحقيقة، كمية مأهولة من المعلومات
in the universe around us comes from those accidents,
في الكون حولنا تأتي من تلك الحوادث،
and not just from the fundamental laws.
وليس فقط من مجرد القوانين الأساسية.
Now, it's often said that getting closer and closer
الآن، يقال دائماً أن الإقتراب أكثر وأكثر
to the fundamental laws by examining phenomena at low energies, and then higher energies,
من القوانين الأساسية عبر إختبار ظاهرة تحت طاقة منخفضة، ثم طاقات أعلى،
and then higher energies, or short distances, and then shorter distances,
ثم طاقات أعلى، أو مسافة قصيرة، ثم مسافات أقصر،
and then still shorter distances, and so on, is like peeling the skin of an onion.
ثم مسافات أقصر، وهلمجرا، هو مثل تقشير الجلد من البصل.
And we keep doing that,
ونحن نواصل فعل ذلك،
and build more powerful machines, accelerators for particles.
ونبني المزيد من الماكينات الخارقة، ومسرعات الجسيمات.
We look deeper and deeper into the structure of particles,
نحن ننظر أعمق وأعمق داخل هياكل الجسيمات هذه،
and in that way we get probably closer and closer to this fundamental law.
وبتلك الطريقة يمكننا على الأرجح الوصول لأقرب وأقرب من هذا القانون الأساسي.
Now, what happens is that as we do that, as we peel these skins of the onion,
الآن، ما يحدث هو بينما نفعل نحن ذلك، بينما نقشر هذا البصل،
and we get closer and closer to the underlying law,
ونقترب أكثر وأكثر من القانون الأساسي،
we see that each skin has something in common with the previous one,
نحن نرى أن لكل قشرة شئ مشترك مع القشرة السابقة،
and with the next one. We write them out mathematically,
ومع القشرة التالية. نقوم بكتابتها رياضياً،
and we see they use very similar mathematics.
ونرى أنها تستخدم رياضيات شبيهة.
They require very similar mathematics.
إنها تتطلب رياضيات متشابهة جداً.
That is absolutely remarkable, and that is a central feature
ذلك بالطبع أمر رائع جداً، وتلك السمة المركزية
of what I'm trying to say today.
لما أحاول قوله اليوم.
Newton called it -- that's Newton, by the way -- that one.
أطلق عليها نيوتن-- ذلك نيوتن بالمناسبة -- ذلك الشخص.
This one is Albert Einstein. Hi, Al! And anyway,
هذا هو إلبرت إينشتاين. مرحباً، آل! وعلى أي حال،
he said, "nature conformable to herself" -- personifying nature as a female.
قال، " الطبيعة مطابقة لنفسها" -- تشخيص الطبيعة كأنثى.
And so what happens is that the new phenomena,
ولذا فما يحدث هو أن الظاهرة الجديدة،
the new skins, the inner skins of the slightly smaller skins of the onion
القشور الجديدة، القشور الداخلية لقشور أصغر قليلاً من البصل
that we get to, resemble the slightly larger ones.
التي نصلها، تشبه التي تكبرها قليلاً.
And the kind of mathematics that we had for the previous skin
ونوع الرياضيات التي أستخدمناها في القشرة السابقة
is almost the same as what we need for the next skin.
هي تقريباً نفسها التي نحتاجها للقشرة التالية.
And that's why the equations look so simple.
ولهذا تبدو المعادلات في غاية البساطة.
Because they use mathematics we already have.
لأنها تستخدم رياضيات موجودة لدينا بالفعل.
A trivial example is this: Newton found the law of gravity,
مثال ساذج على هذا: أخترع نيوتن قانون الجاذبية،
which goes like one over the square of the distance between the things gravitated.
الذي يقول أن واحد على مربع المسافة بين الاشياء المنجذبة.
Coulomb, in France, found the same law for electric charges.
كولوم، في فرنسا، أخترع نفس القانون للتيارات الكهربية.
Here's an example of this similarity.
ها هو مثال لهذا التشابه.
You look at gravity, you see a certain law.
تنظر للجاذبية، ترى قانون محدد.
Then you look at electricity. Sure enough. The same rule.
ثم تنظر للكهربائية. بكل تأكيد. نفس القانون.
It's a very simple example.
إنه مثال بسيط للغاية.
There are lots of more sophisticated examples.
هناك الكثير من الأمثلة الأكثر تعقيداً.
Symmetry is very important in this discussion.
التناظر مهم جداً في هذا النقاش.
You know what it means. A circle, for example,
تعرفون ما تعنية. الدائرة على سبيل المثال،
is symmetric under rotations about the center of the circle.
هي متناظرة في إطار الدوران في مركز الدائرة.
You rotate around the center of the circle, the circle remains unchanged.
تقوم بالدوران حول مركز الدائرة، وتظل الدائرة بلا تغيير.
You take a sphere, in three dimensions, you rotate around the center of the sphere,
تقوم بأخذ المخروط ، بثلاثة أبعاد، تقوم بالدوران حول مركز المخروط،
and all those rotations leave the sphere alone.
وكل هذه الدورات تترك المخروط لوحده.
They are symmetries of the sphere.
إنها متناظرة للمخروط.
So we say, in general, that there's a symmetry
لذا فنحن نقول، عامة، ان هناك تناظر
under certain operations if those operations leave the phenomenon,
في عمليات محددة إذا كانت تلك العمليات تترك الظاهرة،
or its description, unchanged.
أو شرح الظاهرة، بلا تغيير.
Maxwell's equations are of course symmetrical
معادلات ماكسويل بالطبع متناظرة
under rotations of all of space.
في الدوران في كل الفراغ.
Doesn't matter if we turn the whole of space around by some angle,
لا يهم إن قمنا بقلب كل الفراغ على عقب بزاوية ما،
it doesn't leave the -- doesn't change the phenomenon of electricity or magnetism.
إنها لا تترك -- لا تغيّر ظاهرة الكهرباء أو المغنطيسية.
There's a new notation in the 19th century that expressed this,
هناك معادلة جديدة في القرن التاسع عشر التي تشرح هذا،
and if you use that notation, the equations get a lot simpler.
وإذا استخدمت تلك المعادلة، فأن المعادلات تصبح أسهل بكثير.
Then Einstein, with his special theory of relativity,
بعد ذلك إينشتاين، مع هذه النظرية الخاصة للنسبية،
looked at a whole set of symmetries of Maxwell's equations,
نظر في المجموعة الكاملة لمتناظرات معادلات ماكسويل،
which are called special relativity.
التي تسمى بالنسبية الخاصة.
And those symmetries, then, make the equations even shorter, and even prettier, therefore.
وهذه المتناظرات، عندها، تجعل المعادلات أقصر حتى، وأجمل حينئذ.
Let's look. You don't have to know what these things mean, doesn't make any difference.
لننظر. لا تحتاج لمعرفة ما تعنيه هذه الأشياء، لن تحدث أي فرق.
But you can just look at the form. (Laughter) You can look at the form.
لكن يمكنك مجرد رؤية الشكل. (ضحك). يمكنك النظر في الشكل.
You see above, at the top, a long list
وترى في الأعلى، قائمة طويلة
of equations with three components for the three directions of space: x, y and z.
من المعادلات بثلاثة عناصر للإتجاهات الثلاثة للفراغ: x, y و z.
Then, using vector analysis, you use rotational symmetry, and you get this next set.
ثم، بإستخدام تحليل القوة الموجهة، تستخدم التناظر الدائرة، وتحصل على هذه المجموعة التالية.
Then you use the symmetry of special relativity and you get an even simpler set
ثم تستخدم تناظر النسبية الخاصة وتحصل على مجموعة أبسط حتى
down here, showing that symmetry exhibits better and better.
هناك، تظهر أن التناظر يتحسن بصورة أفضل وأفضل.
The more and more symmetry you have, the better you exhibit the simplicity and elegance of the theory.
كلما قمت بتناظر أكثر وأكثر، كلما تحسن من بساطة وأناقة النظرية.
The last two, the first equation says that electric charges and currents
المعادلتان الأخيرتان، تقول أن الشحنات الكهربية والتيارات
give rise to all the electric and magnetic fields.
تقوم بزيادة كل المجالات الكهربية والمغنطيسية.
The next -- second -- equation says that there is no magnetism other than that.
المعادلة التالية -- الثانية-- تقول أنه لا يوجد مغنطة أكثر من ذلك.
The only magnetism comes from electric charges and currents.
المغنطيسية الوحيدة تأتي من الشحنات الكهربية والتيارات.
Someday we may find some slight hole in that argument.
ربما نجد يوم ما ثقب بسيط في تلك الحجة.
But for the moment, that's the case.
لكن للحظة، تلك هي الحالة.
Now, here is a very exciting development that many people have not heard of.
الآن، ها هو تطوّر مثير للغاية ربما لم يسمع الكثيرون منكم عنه.
They should have heard of it, but it's a little tricky to explain in technical detail,
كان يجب أن يسمعوا به، لكنه مخادع قليلاً لأقوم بشرحه بتفاصيل فنية،
so I won't do it. I'll just mention it. (Laughter)
لذا فلن أفعل ذلك. سأذكره فقط. (ضحك)
But Chen Ning Yang, called by us "Frank" Yang -- (Laughter)
لكن تشين نينغ يانغ، نطلق عليه" فرانيك" يانغ-- (ضحك)
-- and Bob Mills put forward, 50 years ago,
-- وبوب ميلز وضعا قدماً، قبل 50 سنة مضت،
this generalization of Maxwell's equations, with a new symmetry.
هذا التعميم لمعادلات ماكسويل، مع تناظر جديد.
A whole new symmetry.
تناظر جديد كلياً.
Mathematics very similar, but there was a whole new symmetry.
رياضيات متشابهة للغاية، لكن كان هناك تناظر جديد كلياً.
They hoped that this would contribute somehow to particle physics
كان أملهم أن هذا سيسهم بطريقة ما لفيزياء الجسيمات
-- didn't. It didn't, by itself, contribute to particle physics.
-- لم تفعل، من نفسها، المساهمة في فيزياء الجسيمات.
But then some of us generalized it further. And then it did!
لكن بعد ذلك قام بعض منا بتعميمها أكثر. ثم بعد ذلك ساهمت!
And it gave a very beautiful description of the strong force and of the weak force.
وقد أعطت شرحاً جميلاً جداً للقوى القوية والقوى الضعيفة.
So here we say, again, what we said before:
لذا نقول هناك، مجدداً، ما قلته سابقاً:
that each skin of the onion shows a similarity to the adjoining skins.
أن كل قشرة من البصلة تعرض تشابهاً للقشور المجاورة.
So the mathematics for the adjoining skins is very similar to what we need for the new one.
لذا فرياضيات القشورة المجاورة شبيهة جداً لما نحتاجه للقشور الجديدة.
And therefore it looks beautiful
ولذا فهي تبدو جميلة.
because we already know how to write it in a lovely, concise way.
لأننا نعرف بالفعل كيفية كتابتها بطريقة موجزة وجميلة.
So here are the themes. We believe there is a unified theory underlying all the regularities.
إذا ها هو الموضوع. نعتقد أن هناك نظرية موحدة تحكم كل النظم.
Steps toward unification exhibit the simplicity.
خطوات تجاه الوحدة تبيّن البساطة.
Symmetry exhibits the simplicity.
التناظر يبيّن البساطة.
And then there is self-similarity across the scales -- in other words,
ثم أن هناك تناظر ذاتي بين مختلف الأحجام-- بكلمات أخرى،
from one skin of the onion to another one.
من قشرة بصلة للقشرة الأخرى.
Proximate self-similarity. And that accounts for this phenomenon.
قريب من تشابهها ذاتياً. وهذا مهم لهذه الظاهرة.
That will account for why beauty is a successful criterion for selecting the right theory.
سينحسب ذلك على لماذا الجمال هو طريقة ناجحة للنظرية الصحيحة.
Here's what Newton himself said:
ها هو ما قاله نيوتن بنفسه:
"Nature is very consonant and conformable to her self."
" الطبيعة منسجمة تماماً ومتطابقة مع نفسها."
One thing he was thinking of is something that most of us take for granted today,
أحد الأشياء التي كان يفكر بها هي شئ يأخذها معظمنا كأمر مسلّم به،
but in his day it wasn't taken for granted.
لكن خلال أيامه لم يكن مسلّم به.
There's the story, which is not absolutely certain to be right, but a lot of people told it.
هناك قصة، التي هي ليست مؤكد أنها صحيحة، لكن يرويها الكثير من الناس.
Four sources told it. That when they had the plague in Cambridge,
حكاها أربعة أشخاص. وذلك عند إصابتهم بالطاعون في كمبيردج،
and he went down to his mother's farm -- because the university was closed --
وذهب لمزرعة والدته-- لأن الجامعة كانت مغلقة--
he saw an apple fall from a tree, or on his head or something.
رأى تفاحة تسقط من الشجرة، أو على رأسه أو شئ ما.
And he realized suddenly that the force that drew the apple down to the earth
وقد أدرك فجأة أن القوى التي سحبت التفاحة إلى أسفل إلى الأرض
could be the same as the force regulating the motions of the planets and the moon.
قد تكون نفس القوى التي تنظم الحركات للكواكب والقمر.
That was a big unification for those days, although today we take it for granted.
كان ذلك توحيد كبير لتلك الأيام، رغماً عن أننا نأخذها اليوم كأمر مسلّم به.
It's the same theory of gravity.
إنه نفس نظرية الجاذبية.
So he said that this principle of nature, consonance:
لذا فقد قال أن هذا المبدأ من الطبيعة، منسجم:
"This principle of nature being very remote from the conceptions of philosophers,
" هذا المبدأ للطبيعة أن تكون بعيداً جداً من مفاهيم الفلاسفة،
I forbore to describe it in that book,
أنا أمتنع عن وصفها في ذلك الكتاب،
lest I should be accounted an extravagant freak ... "
على الأقل ينبغي أخذها في الإعتبار كشئ غريب باسراف..."
That's what we all have to watch out for, (Laughter) especially at this meeting.
ذلك ما علينا جميعاً مراقبته. (ضحك). خصوصاً في هذه الجلسة.
" ... and so prejudice my readers against all those things which were the main design of the book."
"...ولذا فتحيّز القراء ضد كل هذه الأشياء التي كانت التصميم الرئيسي للكتاب."
Now, who today would claim that as a mere conceit of the human mind?
الآن، من سيدعي اليوم أن ذلك مجرد نتيجة لغرور العقل البشري؟
That the force that causes the apple to fall to the ground
تلك القوى التي تسببت في سقوط التفاحة على الأرض
is the same force that causes the planets and the moon to move around,
هي نفس القوى التي تتسبب في تحريك الكواكب والقمر ،
and so on? Everybody knows that. It's a property of gravitation.
وهملجرا؟ يعلم الجميع ذلك. إنها خاصية الجاذبية.
It's not something in the human mind. The human mind can, of course, appreciate it
إنها شئ في العقل البشري. يستطيع العقل البشري بالطبع، تقديرها
and enjoy it, use it, but it's not -- it doesn't stem from the human mind.
والإستمتاع بها، إستخدامها، لكنها ليست -- إنها لا تنبع من العقل البشري.
It stems from the character of gravity.
إنها تنبع من طبيعة الجاذبية.
And that's true of all the things we're talking about.
وذلك صحيح لكل الأشياء التي نتحدث عنها.
They are properties of the fundamental law.
هناك خواص للمبدأ الأساسي.
The fundamental law is such that the different skins of the onion resemble one another,
إن المبدأ الأساسي هو مثل تلك القشور المختلفة للبصلة تشبه بعضها البعض،
and therefore the math for one skin allows you to express beautifully and simply
وعليه فان رياضيات قشرة واحدة تتيح لنا التعبير بكل جمال وبساطة
the phenomenon of the next skin.
عن ظاهرة القشرة التالية.
I say here that Newton did a lot of things that year:
أقول هنا أن نيوتن فعل الكثير من الأشياء في تلك السنة:
gravity, the laws of motion, the calculus, white light composed of all the colors of the rainbow.
الجاذبية، قوانين الحركة، حساب التفاضل والتكامل، الضوء الأبيض المكوّن من كل ألوان لقوس قزح.
And he could have written quite an essay on "What I Did Over My Summer Vacation."
وأستطاع كتابة مقال حول " ماذا فعلت في عطلتي الصيفية."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we don't have to assume these principles as separate metaphysical postulates.
إذاً لا يجب أن تفترض أن هذه المبادئ والمسلمات الميتافيزيقية منفصلة.
They follow from the fundamental theory.
إنها مرتبطة من النظرية الأساسية.
They are what we call emergent properties.
إنها ما نسميه الخصائص الناشئة.
You don't need -- you don't need something more to get something more.
لا نحتاج -- لا نحتاج لشئ أكثر للحصول على شئ أكثر.
That's what emergence means.
ذلك ما تعنيه ناشئة.
Life can emerge from physics and chemistry, plus a lot of accidents.
يمكن للحياة أن تنشأ من الفيزياء والكيمياء، بالإضافة للكثير من الحوادث.
The human mind can arise from neurobiology and a lot of accidents,
يمكن للعقل البشري أن ينشأ من بيولوجيا الأعصاب والكثير من الحوادث،
the way the chemical bond arises from physics and certain accidents.
الطريقة التي تنشأ بها الرابطة الكيميائية من الفيزياء وحوادث معينة.
It doesn't diminish the importance of these subjects
إنها لا تقلل من أهمية هذه المواضيع
to know that they follow from more fundamental things, plus accidents.
لنعرف أنها مرتبطة بالكثير من الأشياء الأساسية، إضافةً للحوادث.
That's a general rule, and it's critically important to realize that.
ذلك هو قانون عام، وإدراكه مهم بشدة.
You don't need something more in order to get something more.
أنت لا تحتاج لشئ إكثر للحصول على شئ أكثر.
People keep asking that when they read my book, "The Quark and the Jaguar,"
يظل الناس يسألون عن ذلك حينما يقرأون كتابي، كوارك وجاكوار.
and they say, "Isn't there something more beyond what you have there?"
وأنا أقول، " إليس هناك شئ أكثر مما لديكم هناك؟"
Presumably, they mean something supernatural.
ويفترض، أنهم يعنون شيئاً خارقاً.
Anyway, there isn't. (Laughter)
على أي حال، لا يوجد. (ضحك)
You don't need something more to explain something more.
لا تحتاج لشئ أكثر لشرح شئ أكثر.
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكراً جزيلاً لكم. (تصفيق)